## Contact

#### Email:

sthan 18@ terpmail.umd.edu

#### **Phone:**

(410)-419-2169

#### Address:

2617 Luiss Deane Drive, Parkville, Maryland, USA

## **Online Portfolio**

#### **Personal Website:**

https://www.linkedin.com/in/nikesh-shrestha-3518ba11b/

#### Education

Bachelor of Science Mechanical Engineering University of Maryland College Park, MD, USA GPA: 3.5/4.0

Calvert Hall College High School Towson, MD, USA GPA: 4.0/4.0

## Skills

## **Software & Programming**

3D Design (SolidWorks, Inventor, Fusion360)

MATLAB

Microsoft Office

Python, C++

LabView, Simulink

ANSYS Workbench (FEA)

#### **Technical Skills**

Product and Process Design DFMA Lean Manufacturing Six Sigma Human Reliability Analysis ASME Y14.5 GD&T

#### **Machines**

3D Printing, Bandsaw, Lathe, Solder, CNC

## Languages

Fluent in English & Nepali Conversant in French & Hindi

# Nikesh Shrestha

Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering

## Summary

Mechanical Engineering graduate from the University of Maryland – College Park (Aug. 2018 – Dec. 2021) with experience in research and engineering projects. Awarded multiple awards for excellence in education. Experienced various technical and soft skills through courses, projects, self-education, and involvement in multiple organizations.

## **Work Experience**

Nano Biochip for Disease Detection, Diagnosis and Monitoring (New Jersey Institute of Technology) (NSF REU)

[Jun. 2020 – Aug. 2020]

- Research Assistant in NJIT Advanced Energy Systems and Microdevices Laboratory.
- Developed MATLAB algorithm for autonomous measurement of wetting angles from images.
- Investigated the visualization and characterization of fluid drop on a surface treated PDMS, and *fluid flow dynamics of in microchannel* for implementation in passive plasma separation.

**Undergraduate Teaching Assistant** (University of Maryland) [Aug. 2020 – Dec. 2021]

- Undergraduate Teaching Assistant for Electronics and Instrumentation II; Vibrations, Controls and Optimization I; Introductory C++ & MATLAB Programming Course.
- Led lab and studio sessions with 20 to 30 students.
- Guided students with understanding course concepts and applying them to assignments.

## **Technical Experience**

# Project: Redesigning Braking System for Triathlon Bikes

- Team Leader and Team Scribe.
- Designed and built a hydraulic braking system integrated inside aerobars for Triathlon bikes.
- Implemented the *Product and Process Design Principles & Lean Manufacturing Principles*.
- Used MATLAB, SolidWorks, Stack-up and GD&T for design, analysis, and simulation.
- Used additive and subtractive manufacturing machines for assembly.

#### **Project: Time Series Analysis: Location Prediction of Dynamical System**

- Applied *Machine Learning Algorithm* to forecast the location and orientation of a Navy Battleship.
- Implemented Supervised Probabilistic Model: Variational Sparse Gaussian Processes.
- Utilized *PyTorch* and Probabilistic Programming language *PyMC3*.

#### Project: Designed and built an Autonomous Robot

- Designed and built a sensor car that autonomously follows the operator.
- Utilized *Arduino Uno microcontroller*, *PIR and Ultrasonic sensors*, and *actuators (DC and Servo Motors)* to autonomously detect and follow the operator at various speeds.
- Programmed using Arduino IDE and Processing 3 for operation and demonstration.

#### Project: Disassembly and Mechanical Analysis of HP Vista Personal Computer

- Team Leader and Team Scribe.
- Design, Reliability and Cost analysis of Graphics and Memory Controller chip, and RAM.
- Visualized the manufacturing considerations for thermo-mechanical and vibrational effects.
- Disassembled individual components on a computer motherboard for analysis.
- Used *subtractive manufacturing* machines for breakdown and polishing of components.

# **Awards & Honors**

- National Science Foundation REU Fellowship
- Dean's List for Outstanding Students
- Office of Multi-ethnic Student Education Academic Excellence Award
- G. Lee and Lou Ann Lushbaugh, Jr. Endowed Scholarship
- Sean and Sarah Durbin Scholarship
- Bechtel Corporate Partner Scholarship